<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<office>
    <id>assistant-secretary-of-state-for-european-affairs-1983</id>
    <old-ids/>
    <name>Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs</name>
    <category>assistant-secretary-geo</category>
    <rank>assistant-secretary-of-state</rank>
    <valid-from>1949-05-26</valid-from>
    <valid-until>1983-09-14</valid-until>
    <predecessors/>
    <successors>
        <successor>assistant-secretary-of-state-for-european-and-canadian-affairs-1999</successor>
    </successors>
    <note>
        <div>
            <p>The Department of State established the position of Assistant Secretary of State for
                European Affairs in 1949, after the Commission on Organization of the Executive
                Branch of Government (Hoover Commission) recommended that certain offices be
                upgraded to bureau level and after Congress had increased the number of Assistant
                Secretaries of State from six to ten (May 26, 1949; P.L. 81-73; 63 Stat. 111).
                The Department of State first established a Division of Western European Affairs in
                1909, which handled European nations primarily bordering on the Atlantic Ocean and
                their colonies. The Division of Near Eastern Affairs handled relations with most
                Central, Eastern, and Southern European countries until after World War I. During
                the interwar period, responsibility for much of Central and Eastern Europe shifted
                to the Division of European Affairs, although Greece, Turkey, and Cyprus were
                handled as part of the Near East until Apr 18, 1974. Following World War II, the
                Department completed the transfer of responsibility for the former colonies of
                European nations, except Canada, to the Bureau of Near Eastern, South Asian, and
                African Affairs and the Bureau of Far Eastern Affairs.</p>
        </div>
    </note>
    <created-by>jacksonse</created-by>
    <created-date>2016-07-28</created-date>
    <last-modified-by>jacksonse</last-modified-by>
    <last-modified-date>2016-07-29</last-modified-date>
</office>